Finding Aid for Barbara MacAdam papers, 1957-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Barbara MacAdam papers
1957-2011
1980-2005
MacAdam, Barbara
2011106 Aa 2
Barbara MacAdam was a librarian for the University of Michigan Library system from 1979 to 2011. Titles have included head of Undergraduate Library, head of Reference and Instruction, and Associate University Librarian for Public Services. The collection documents projects and operation of the University Library during MacAdam's work there, as well as course material from her position as lecturer within the School of Information and College of Literature, Science, and the Arts
7 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Material was donated by Barbara MacAdam in July 2011 (Donor no. 10599 )
Periodic additions to the collection are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Barbara MacAdam earned her bachelor's degree with high honors in English from the University of Michigan in 1972. She continued her studies there, earning her Master of Arts in Library Science degree in 1979.
Her career as a librarian within the University of Michigan Library system began when she was named an assistant librarian for the Undergraduate Library in 1979. She continued in this capacity for two years, after which she became head of Media Services at the Medical School's Learning Resource center from 1981 to 1982. From 1982 to 1985, MacAdam served as coordinator for Access and Automated Services in the Undergraduate Library. In 1985, she became the acting head of the Undergraduate Library and became permanent head in 1987. She remained head of the Undergraduate Library until 1999, when she became head of Reference and Instruction in the Harlan Hatcher Graduate Library, a position she held until 2008. In 2008, her title became Associate University Librarian for Public Services.
In addition to her work as librarian, MacAdam served as lecturer within the School of Information (formerly School of Information and Library Studies) and College of Literature, Science, and Arts. Courses taught within the School of Information include ILS 755 ("Instruction in the Use of Information,"), ILS 618 ("Academic and Research Libraries,"), SI 695 ("The University Learning Environment,"), and SI 647 ("Introduction to Information Resources and Services,").Within the College of Literature, Science, and the Arts, she has taught Honors 251 ("The Structure of Inquiry in the Information Age," later renamed "Knowledge and Society in the Information Age,") and Communication 250 ("Information Gathering for Mass Media,").
MacAdam's many honors and awards include the Virginia Voss Memorial Award for Writing (1972), John Cotton Dana Award from the American Library Association (1987), Diversity Award (1996 and 2011), Miriam Dudley Instruction Librarian Award (1996), and University Librarian Recognition Award (2004). She was also inducted into Phi Beta Kappa (1972) and Beta Phi Mu (1979) while at the University of Michigan.
MacAdam has written many articles and made numerous presentations for library profession journals and conferences. She has also served on many committees for the Association of College and Research Libraries division of the American Library Association, Michigan Library Association, and University of Michigan. MacAdam retired from the University of Michigan in 2011.
The Barbara MacAdam Papers document projects, programs, and events undertaken by the University of Michigan Library system during MacAdam's work there, which included almost 15 years as head of the Undergraduate Library and 10 years as head of Reference and Instruction at the Graduate Library. It also includes course material from her position as lecturer within the School of Information (formerly School of Information and Library Studies) and College of Literature, Science, and the Arts (Honors Program and Department of Communication). The records are arranged into nine series: Biographical, Course Material, Facilities, Graduate Library South Building Renovation, Mirlyn Implementation (2004), Miscellaneous Library Material, Projects/Collaborations, Projects/Committees, and Undergraduate Library.
Subjects:
MacAdam, Barbara, 1947-; Libraries--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Library.; University of Michigan. School of Information.; University of Michigan. Undergraduate Library.
- Biographical
  The Biographical series contains MacAdam's Curriculum Vita.
  - Curriculum Vita, 2011 (Box 1)
- Course Material
  The Course Material series includes syllabi, handouts, lecture notes, readings, and grades for Communication 250 and 500, Honors Program 251, and ILS 755. Also included are coursepacks for Honors 251. Communication 250 (originally 500) was a required course for communication majors focusing on how critical thinking and information synthesis are impacted by technology and new media, and was taught jointly by the University Library and Department of Communication. Honors 251 was developed and taught as an honors sophomore seminar in LS&A. The series also documents collaboration between the University Library and School of Information to create an undergraduate course, which resulted in the formation of Honors 251.
  - Communication 250 and 500 (Information Gathering for Mass Media)
    - 1985, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1986, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1987 (Box 1)
    - 1988, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1989 (Box 1)
    - 1990 (Box 1)
    - 1991 (Box 1)
  - Honors 251 (The Structure of Inquiry in the Information Age, later renamed Knowledge and Society in the Information Age)
    - Coursepacks
      - W, 1994 (Box 1)
      - W, 1996 (Box 1)
      - W, 1997 (Box 1)
    - General, 1992-1997 (Box 1)
  - Information and Library Science (ILS) 755 (Instruction in the Use of Information), 1988-1991; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Joint Educational Program
    - Annenberg Project, 1995 (Box 1)
    - General, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
- Facilities
  The Facilities series documents efforts between 2004-2007 to identify the University Library's strengths and areas for improvement and plan for future needs and developments. It includes the Library Facilities Master Plan, material from the Library Learning Spaces Task Force, and plans submitted by various architectural firms.
  - Library Facilities Master Plan, 2006 (Box 2)
  - Library Learning Spaces Task Force, 2004-2007; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Shapiro Library Facility Master Plan & Conceptual Design Services, 2006; 2 folders (Box 2)
- Graduate Library South Building Renovation (Connie Dunlap Files)
  The Graduate Library South Building Renovation series documents construction work at the Graduate Library in the mid 1970s. It includes budget information, bulletins, construction meeting minutes, and memos. The material in this series was inherited from Connie Dunlap, who was Deputy Associate Director for Public Services during the 1970s
  - Addenda, 1973-1974 (Box 2)
  - Book Move, 1973-1975 (Box 2)
  - Budget, 1972-1974 (Box 2)
  - Bulletins, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
  - Construction Meeting Minutes, 1972-1975 (Box 2)
  - Furniture, 1974 (Box 2)
  - General, 1973-1976 (Box 2)
  - Memos, 1972-1975; 2 folders (Box 2)
- Mirlyn Implementation (2004)
  The Mirlyn Implementation (2004) series focuses on material relating to the planning for and implementation of the new version of Mirlyn, the Library's online information system and catalog. It replaced MirlynWeb and MirlynClassic with a single web-based interface and was implemented in fall 2004. The series contains marketing/publicity material announcing the rollout of the new version, material on the Public Gateway Design, and specifications.
  - General, 2005 (Box 2)
  - Marketing/Publicity, 2003-2004 (Box 2)
  - Public Gateway Design, 2001; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Specifications, 2004 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Library Material
  The Miscellaneous Library Material series includes a variety of resources from MacAdam's time at the University Library. The two main components of the series are annual reports from 1981 to 1998 and annual goals, both MacAdam's personal goals and goals for the Undergraduate Library, from 1985 to 1998. Also included is material from the Presidential Initiative Fund, Undergraduate Initiative, Executive Research Service, and plans and visions for the connector linking the Hatcher Graduate Library with the Shapiro Undergraduate Library.
  - Annual Reports, 1981-1998; 16 folders (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1990-1998 (Box 3)
  - Executive Research Service, 1987-2003 (Box 3)
  - General Reports, Plans, Statements, 1989-2003 (Box 3)
  - Goals, 1985-1998; 9 folders (Box 3)
  - Hatcher/Shapiro Connector, 1995 (Box 3)
  - Presidential Initiative Fund, 1994-1996 (Box 3)
  - Primary Librarian Staff Handbook, undated (Box 3)
  - Undergraduate Initiative, 1986-1990; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - User Guides, 1988-1998 (Box 3)
  - User-Study Project Report, 1991 (Box 3)
- Projects/Collaborations
  The Projects/Collaborations series documents University Library projects and collaborations with other University of Michigan units and organizations. This includes collaboration with the Alumni Association to develop their new educational emphasis; the "Computers in Composition" collaboration with LS&A to analyze how computers might change writing and thinking, the Gateway Project, which created the first institutional home page for the university; the creation of living/learning centers and residential communities; and collaboration between the Library and Information Technology Division to form the Microcomputer Center on campus. Also documented in this series is the collaboration between the Library and Housing to form the residence hall library system, which was ultimately discontinued; the UM Instructional Environment (originally Digital Classroom), a Library-led collaboration that became the blueprint for the original Coursetools, subsequently CTools; early use in the Library of UMTV, the original campus cable network; and Virtual University, originally a collaboration between Michigan colleges and universities and industry to provide online education to workers, but later focusing more on providing online courses to K-12 students.
  - Alumni Association, 1995-1998 (Box 4)
  - Computers in Composition, 1986-1988; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Faculty Exploratory, 1996; 2004 (Box 4)
  - Gateway Project, 1992-1994; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Living/Learning Centers and Residential Learning Communities, 1994-1999; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - L-shaped Building, 2000 (Box 4)
  - Microcomputer Policy, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
  - Residence Hall Libraries, 1986-2002 (Box 4)
  - UM Instructional Environment (UMIE), originally called Digital Classroom, 1994-1998; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - UMTV, 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - Virtual University, 1996-1997; 2 folders (Box 4)
- Projects/Committees
  The Projects/Committees series includes extensive material concerning reference projects and the Research Library Residency Program. Reference files include material from projects and services such as Ask Us Now, Interactive Reference Assistance, and Information Coordinators Group, as well as the Committee on Institutional Cooperation Online Reference Conference and Second Annual Digital Reference Conference. Research Library Residency Program files document the program's efforts to provide recently graduated librarians with opportunities for advanced training and practical work experience at the University Library. Also included in the series are files on the Academic Computing Advisory Committee, Code Implementation Review Committee, Council on undergraduate Affairs, "Future of the University Library" Report, UM Advisory Panel to the President, and Value Centered Management.
  - Academic Computing Advisory Committee, 1995-1996 (Box 5)
  - Code Implementation Review Committee, 1998-1999 (Box 5)
  - Council on Undergraduate Affairs, 1989-1993; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - "Future of the University Library" Report, 1996 (Box 5)
  - Reference
    - Virtual Reference
      - Ask Us Now, undated (Box 5)
      - Committee on Institutional Cooperation (CIC) Online Reference Conference, 2001 (Box 5)
      - General, 1996-2006; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Interactive Reference Assistance, 1995-1996 (Box 5)
      - Second Annual Digital Reference Conference, Seattle, 2000 (Box 5)
    - Graduate Library
      - General, 2000 (Box 5)
      - Information Coordinators Group, 1998-1999 (Box 5)
  - Research Library Residency Program
    - Advisory Committee, 1985 (Box 5)
    - General, 1982-1997 (Box 5)
    - Proposals, 1986-1995 (Box 5)
    - Seminar, 1983 (Box 5)
  - UM Advisory Panel to the President (UMAP), 1996 (Box 5)
  - Value Centered Management (VCM), 1996 (Box 5)
- Undergraduate Library
  The Undergraduate Library series is the largest in the collection. It contains extensive material on the Library's early years, Peer Information Counseling Program, Shapiro Building Project, Sight and Sound Center, student assistants handbooks, and 30th Anniversary. Files on the early years of the Undergraduate Library include personnel records, photos, and purchases. Peer Information Counseling Program files document the history of the nationally recognized Library program supporting the needs of a diverse student community. The Shapiro Building Project files include plans, proposals, and schedules for the transformation of the Undergraduate Library in the early 1990s. The Sight and Sound Center files document the transition and ultimate closing of the original media center in the Library as media formats evolved. The student assistants handbooks were designed to support and develop the skills and understanding of student assistants, an important part of the Library's staffing model. The 30th Anniversary files include photos, flyers, programs, and display items for the 30th Anniversary of the Undergraduate Library in 1988. Other folders within the series include material on topics such as the Branstrom Prize, collection development policy, Debate Institute, and UGLI newsletters.
  - "1981-82 and 1982-83 Library Use Studies" Final Report, 1983 (Box 6)
  - Articles, 1965-1987 (Box 6)
  - Branstrom Prize, 1964-1981 (Box 6)
  - Collection Development, 1973-1985 (Box 6)
  - Copyright, 1976-1979 (Box 6)
  - Debate Institute, 1988-2000; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Early Years
    - Personnel and Position Records, circa late, 1980s (Box 6)
    - Photos, circa, 1960s (Box 6)
    - Purchases, 1957-1969 (Box 6)
    - "The Undergraduate Library," American Library Association book, 1970 (Box 6)
    - Visitors Register, 1959 (Box 6)
  - Education Library, 1973-1980 (Box 6)
  - General Correspondence, 1979-1995 (Box 6)
  - Peer Information Counseling Program (PIC)
    - General, 1986-1995; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Minority Support Center Proposal, 1984-1985 (Box 6)
    - Newsletters, 1988-1992 (Box 6)
    - Papers, 1987-1988 (Box 6)
  - Public Service Unit Heads Meeting Minutes, 1979-1980 (Box 6)
  - Read, Read, Read, 1983-1998 (Box 6)
  - Reports, Statements, Proposals, Surveys, 1968-2001 (Box 6)
  - SafeWalk, 1987-1995
  - Shapiro Building Project (1991-1994) (Box 6)
    - Adaptive Technology Computing Site, 1993 (Box 7)
    - Draft Proposal for a Science Library on the Central Campus, 1973 (Box 7)
    - First Floor Move, circa early, 1990s (Box 7)
    - Floor, Seating, and Shelving Plans, circa early, 1990s (Box 7)
    - Groundbreaking Ceremony, 1993 (Box 7)
    - Memos, 1993-1994 (Box 7)
    - Moves, 1993 (Box 7)
    - Plans, Proposals, and Statements, 1991-1992 (Box 7)
    - Schedules, 1993-1995 (Box 7)
    - Shapiro Undergraduate Library Dedication, 1995; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Site Visit:, August 5, 1992 (Box 7)
    - Undergraduate Library Before and After Dedication, 1991-1993 (Box 7)
      (photos and negatives)
    - "Undergraduate Library Interior Relocation Plan," Draft, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Sight and Sound Center
    - Closing, 1984-1991; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - General, 1981-1984 (Box 7)
  - Student Assistants' Handbooks
    - 1984-1986, 1988; 1994-1996 (Box 7)
    - Correspondence, Planning, Meeting Minutes, 1984-1986 (Box 7)
  - Student Athlete Study Center Proposals, 1983-1985 (Box 7)
  - Student Lounge, 1980-1987 (Box 7)
  - 30th Anniversary
    - Display, 1987-1988 (Box 7)
    - Photos, Flyer, Button, 1988 (Box 7)
    - Rededication Program, 1989 (Box 7)
    - Symposium, 1987-1988; 2 folders (Box 7)
      (includes negatives)
  - UGLI Newsletters, 1985-1995; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Ugliest Building Award, 1984 (Box 7)
  - Undergraduate Library Renovation, early, 1980s; 1981-1983 (Box 7)
  - User Guides and Information, undated (Box 7)
  - Weeding, 1983-1990 (Box 7)